A Guide to the John G. Kolbe, Inc. Records, 1913-1990
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
John G. Kolbe, Inc. Records, 1913-1990
The Library of Virginia
43555
1.125 cubic feet (3 boxes) and 1 oversize folder
John G. Kolbe, Inc. (Richmond, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of J. A. Kolbe, Richmond, Va., 10 December 2007.
Biographical Information
John G. Kolbe (1887-1953) opened the business that bore his name about 1913 at 212 N. 3rd Street in Richmond, Virginia, selling gas ranges, gas hot water heaters, and other kitchen equipment and supplies, primarily for home use. In 1919, he moved to a new location at 219 E. Grace Street. As the business continued to grow, he moved again, this time to a much larger space at 5 W. Grace Street.
During the Depression, he agreed to take on three partners, young men whose wealthy parents who were looking for business opportunities for their sons. In about 1937, Kolbe made an amicable split with the partners, who wanted to focus on the domestic business, in order to concentrate on a customer base of commercial food service operations. He later rented a store at 311 E. Main Street, and eventually purchased the adjacent buildings at 309 and 313 E. Main as the operation thrived.
In 1953, John G. Kolbe passed away after years of poor health. His son, J. A. Kolbe (1923-2012), often referred to by the nickname "Pete," took over the business. Under his leadership, the company continued to grow, moving to a new location at 1605 Brook Road, and opening branches in Roanoke and Virginia Beach. The younger Kolbe ran the company until the family decided to sell it in 1989.
The above historical information was provided by J. A. Kolbe in a December 2007 letter to the Library of Virginia.
Scope and Content
Records, 1913-1989, of John G. Kolbe, Inc., suppliers of equipment for the preparation and serving of food. John G. Kolbe (1887-1953) started the business about 1913 in Richmond, Virginia. Included are advertisements; newspaper and magazine clippings; materials related to awards given for and by the company, including a scrapbook on the John G. Kolbe Memorial Award; catalogs; correspondence; newsletters; and photographs of company events, individuals, and various store locations in Richmond, Roanoke, and Virginia Beach. Records include "Home Service Manual Containing Recipes of the Home Service Department of John G. Kolbe," 1929; as well as three loose-leaf recipes. Also included are notes by J. A. "Pete" Kolbe (1923- ) on the history of the company, which he took over upon his father's death in 1953.
Contents List
- John G. Kolbe, Inc. records, 1913-1990., Extent: 1.125 cubic feet (3 boxes) and 1 oversize folder. (Box 1-3)
  Arranged as organized by the donor.
  - 1913-1919. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1919-1924. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1924-1937. (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - 1937-1953. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Advertisement, ca. 1949. (Box 64)
  - 1953-1989. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Design awards, 1948, 1951-1952. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Industry relations, 1953-1990. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - John G. Kolbe Memorial Award, 1955-1973. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - John G. Kolbe Memorial Award scrapbook, 1953-1975. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, 1943-1947, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes several issues of Kolbe's Dinner Bell (later called The Kolbe Dinner Bell), 1943-1947, and one issue of Kolbe School Lunch Manager, 1955.
  - Catalog, 1951. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Catalog, 1956. (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Catalog, 1957. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Catalog, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Catalog, 1970. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Catalog, 1977. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Catalog, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Catalog, 1982. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Home Service Manual Containing Recipes of the Home Service Department of John G. Kolbe, 1929, Beverages-Fish. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Home Service Manual Containing Recipes of the Home Service Department of John G. Kolbe, 1929, Frostings-Vegetables. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Home Service Manual cover, 1929. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Recipes, no date. (Box 3, Folder 4)